<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ Copyright (c) 2010. Axon Framework
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->
<chapter id="getting-started" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Getting Started</title>
    <para>So you decided to use axon for your project. Best way to get an idea about the framework
        is to have a look at the sample (TODO link). The sample gives a good idea about the
        structure of a typical project using axon. The sample shows a web project that includes the
        axon framework as libraries.
    </para>
    <para>When starting with axon for your own project, the easiest way is to use maven as a build
        tool. If you feel like creating your own war, you can download the full distribution (TODO
        decide if we want to do this). Be sure to check the optional libraries as well. These are
        not provided by default.
    </para>
    <sect1>
        <title>Download axon</title>
        <para>You can download the axonframework from our google code project page:</para>
        <para>http://code.google.com/p/axonframework/wiki/Downloads?tm=2</para>
        <para>TODO describe what is available for download</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Checkout the sample(s)</title>
        <para>The samples give you a jump start for you own project. At the moment we have an
            address book sample available. There are two different clients in that sample, a flex
            client and a console client. The sample demonstrates the different datasources and
            heavily relies on the event mechanism of axon. More on the sample in Appendix A (TODO
            link).
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Create your own project</title>
        <para>Time to get your feet wet and create your own project. Including axon is
            straigtforward when using maven. This section explains the maven way and gives some
            pointers for those that do not want to use maven.
        </para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Using maven</title>
            <para>If you use maven as your build tool, you need to configure the correct
                dependencies for your project. Since axon is not yet in one of the major maven
                repositories, you have to configure a repository for the axon artifacts in your pom.
            </para>
            <sect3>
                <title>Configuring maven</title>
                <para>Add the following code in your dependencies section:</para>
                <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<dependency>
        <groupId>org.axonframework</groupId>
        <artifactId>axon-core</artifactId>
        <version>0.4</version>
    </dependency>]]></programlisting>
                <para>T make sure your maven installation has access to the axon repository, where
                    the necessary jars and poms are located, you can do at least two things. You can
                    configure your repository proxy to access the axon repository and you can
                    configure your project to look for the axon repository.
                </para>
                <para>If you use a repository proxy, such as Artifactory, configure the following
                    url:
                    <uri>http://axonframework.googlecode.com/svn/repo</uri>
                </para>
                <para>You can also add a repository configuration to you pom.xml:</para>
                <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<repositories>
      <repository>
        <id>axon</id>
        <url>http://axonframework.googlecode.com/svn/repo</url>
      </repository>
    </repositories>]]></programlisting>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Additional dependencies</title>
                <para>Most of the features provided by the Axon Framework are optional and require
                    additional dependencies. We have chosen not to add these dependencies by
                    default, as they would potentioly clutter your project with artifacts you don't
                    need. This section discusses these dependecies and describes in what scenarios
                    you need them.
                </para>
                <simplesect>
                    <title>Event Sourcing</title>
                    <para>The event sourcing repository that is provided in Axon
                        (<code>XStreamFileSystemEventStore</code>) requires XStream. You need to
                        add the following maven dependency to your project to use this repository
                        implementation.
                    </para>
                    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<dependency>
        <groupId>com.thoughtworks.xstream</groupId>
        <artifactId>xstream</artifactId>
        <version>1.3.1</version>
    </dependency>]]></programlisting>
                </simplesect>
                <simplesect>
                    <title>Spring Integration</title>
                    <para>The Axon Framework provides connectors that allow you to publish events on
                        a Spring Integration channel. These connectors require Spring Integration on
                        the classpath. You need the following maven dependency to use these
                        connectors.
                    </para>
                    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<dependency>
        <groupId>org.springframework.integration</groupId>
        <artifactId>spring-integration-core</artifactId>
        <version>1.0.3.RELEASE</version>
    </dependency>]]></programlisting>
                </simplesect>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Without maven</title>
            <para>If you feel the need to use something different than maven to build your project,
                you can use the distribution including dependencies. At the moment we do not really
                support this way to create your project. It should be pretty straightforward to copy
                the required libraries as well as the necessary optional libraries to your
                project.
            </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
