<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
  ~ Copyright (c) 2010. Axon Framework
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<chapter id="getting-started" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Getting Started</title>

    <sect1>
        <title>Obtaining necessary libraries</title>

        <para>If you use maven as your build tool, you need to configure the
            correct dependencies for your project, as well as the repository
            configuration that tells maven where the jars are located.
        </para>

        <sect2>
            <title>Configuring maven</title>

            <para>Add the following code in your dependencies section:</para>

            <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<dependency>
    <groupId>org.axonframework</groupId>
    <artifactId>axon-core</artifactId>
    <version>0.3</version>
</dependency>]]></programlisting>

            <para>Make sure your maven installation has access to the axon repository, where the necessary jars and
                poms are located.
            </para>

            <para>If you use a repository proxy, such as Artifactory, configure the following url:
                <uri>http://axonframework.googlecode.com/svn/repo</uri>
            </para>

            <para>You can also add a repository configuration to you pom.xml:</para>
            <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<repositories>
  <repository>
    <id>axon</id>
    <url>http://axonframework.googlecode.com/svn/repo</url>
  </repository>
</repositories>]]></programlisting>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Additional dependencies</title>

            <para>Most of the features provided by the Axon Framework are optional and require additional
                dependencies. We have chosen not to add these dependencies by default, as they would possibly
                clutter your project with stuff you don't need.
            </para>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Event Sourcing</title>
                <para>
                    The event sourcing repository that is provided in Axon (<code>EventSourcingRepository</code>)
                    requires XStream. You need the following maven dependency to use this repository implementation.
                </para>
                <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<dependency>
    <groupId>com.thoughtworks.xstream</groupId>
    <artifactId>xstream</artifactId>
    <version>1.3.1</version>
</dependency>]]></programlisting>
            </simplesect>

            <simplesect>
                <title>Spring Integration</title>
                <para>
                    The Axon Framework provides connectors that allow you to publish events on a Spring Integration channel. These
                    connectors require Spring Integration on the classpath. You need the following maven dependency to
                    use these connectors.
                </para>
                <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<dependency>
    <groupId>org.springframework.integration</groupId>
    <artifactId>spring-integration-core</artifactId>
    <version>1.0.3.RELEASE</version>
</dependency>]]></programlisting>
            </simplesect>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Creating the CQRS building blocks</title>

        <para/>

        <sect2>
            <title>Building an aggregate</title>

            <para>All aggregates should implement the
                <code>AggregateRoot</code>
                interface. This interface describes that basic
                operations needed by the Repository to store and publish the generated events.
            </para>

            <para>To support you with the implementation, there are two abstract implementations of this interface:
                <code>AbstractAggregateRoot</code>
                and<code>AbstractAnnotatedAggregateRoot</code>.
            </para>

            <para>
                The first is a basic implementation that requires you to override the handle method to implement the
                state change logic. This abstract class provides an apply method that you can call in your business
                logic method to have an event applied. The
                <code>AbstractAggregateRoot</code>
                will keep track of all
                uncommitted applied events and make sure they are forwarded to the EventBus when the aggregate is saved.
            </para>

            <para>The
                <code>AbstractAnnotatedAggregateRoot</code>
                is a specialization of the
                <code>AbstractAggregateRoot</code>
                that provides
                <code>@EventHandler</code>
                annotation support to your aggregate. See
                <xref linkend="annotation-support"/>
                for more information.
            </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Creating event listeners</title>

            <para>Events that have been generated by your aggregates need to be processed. The event bus will take case
                of the dispatching, but the actual processing is done by event listeners.
            </para>

            <para>Each event listener much implement the
                <code>EventListener</code>
                interface. Such implementation can be really
                easy. You do need to make sure that the event listener is subscribed with the event bus.
            </para>

            <para>If you use the annotation support features, you can use the
                <code>AnnotationEventListenerAdapter</code>
                (and
                subclasses) to turn your annotated pojo into a full blown event listener. See annotation support for
                more information.
            </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Choosing an Event Bus</title>

            <para>The
                <code>EventBus</code>
                is the mechanism that dispatches events to the event listeners. Axon Framework
                provides two implementations of the event bus:<code>AsyncEventBus</code>> and
                <code>SynchronousEventBus.</code>
            </para>

            <para>The
                <code>AsyncEventBus</code>
                is the default implementation of choice. It dispatches events asynchronously to all registered
                event listeners in the application. It uses an
                <code>EventSequencingPolicy</code>
                to define the sequential processing requirements
                of events. The
                <code>AsyncEventBus</code>
                can be configured with a
                <code>ExecutorService</code>
                implementation,
                providing maximum control of the number of processor threads.
            </para>

            <para>The
                <code>SynchronousEventBus</code>
                dispatches events in the same thread that publishes them. This is quite useful
                in test scenarios where the overhead of creating and managing application flow over multiple threads is
                unwanted.
            </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
