<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
  ~ Copyright (c) 2010-2012. Axon Framework
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->
<chapter xml:id="architecture-overview" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Technical Overview</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Architectural Overview</title>
        <para>CQRS on itself is a very simple pattern. It only describes that the component of an
            application that processes commands should be separated from the component that
            processes queries. Although this separation is very simple on itself, it provides a
            number of very powerful features when combined with other patterns. Axon provides the
            building block that make it easier to implement the different patterns that can be used
            in combination with CQRS. </para>
        <para>The diagram below shows an example of an extended layout of a CQRS-based event driven
            architecture. The UI component, displayed on the left, interacts with the rest of the
            application in two ways: it sends commands to the application (shown in the top
            section), and it queries the application for information (shown in the bottom section). </para>
        <figure>
            <title>Architecture overview of a CQRS application</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata align="center" format="svg"
                        fileref="detailed-architecture-overview.svg" width="15cm"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata format="png" fileref="detailed-architecture-overview.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Command Handling</title>
            <para>Commands are typically represented by simple and straightforward objects that
                contain all data necessary for a command handler to execute it. A command expresses
                its intent by its name. In Java terms, that means the class name is used to figure
                out what needs to be done, and the fields of the command provide the information
                required to do it. </para>
            <para>The Command Bus receives commands and routes them to the Command Handlers. Each
                command handler responds to a specific type of command and executes logic based on
                the contents of the command. In some cases, however, you would also want to execute
                logic regardless of the actual type of command, such as validation, logging or
                authorization. </para>
            <para>Axon provides building blocks to help you implement a command handling
                infrastructure with these features. These building blocks are thoroughly described
                in <xref linkend="command-handling"/>. </para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Domain Modeling</title>
            <para>The command handler retrieves domain objects (Aggregates) from a repository and
                executes methods on them to change their state. These aggregates typically contain
                the actual business logic and are therefore responsible for guarding their own
                invariants. The state changes of aggregates result in the generation of Domain
                Events. Both the Domain Events and the Aggregates form the domain model. Axon
                provides supporting classes to help you build a domain model. They are described in
                    <xref linkend="domain-modeling"/>. </para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Repositories and Event Stores</title>
            <para>Repositories are responsible for providing access to aggregates. Typically, these
                repositories are optimized for lookup of an aggregate by its unique identifier only.
                Some repositories will store the state of the aggregate itself (using Object
                Relational Mapping, for example), while other store the state changes that the
                aggregate has gone through in an Event Store. The repository is also responsible for
                persisting the changes made to aggregates in its backing storage. </para>
            <para>Axon provides support for both the direct way of persisting aggregates (using
                object-relational-mapping, for example) and for event sourcing. More about
                repositories and event stores can be found in <xref
                    linkend="repositories-and-event-stores"/>. </para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Event Processing </title>
            <para>The event bus dispatches events to all interested event listeners. This can either
                be done synchronously or asynchronously. Asynchronous event dispatching allows the
                command execution to return and hand over control to the user, while the events are
                being dispatched and processed in the background. Not having to wait for event
                processing to complete makes an application more responsive. Synchronous event
                processing, on the other hand, is simpler and is a sensible default. Synchronous
                processing also allows several event listeners to process events within the same
                transaction. </para>
            <para>Event listeners receive events and handle them. Some handlers will update data
                sources used for querying while others send messages to external systems. As you
                might notice, the command handlers are completely unaware of the components that are
                interested in the changes they make. This means that it is very non-intrusive to
                extend the application with new functionality. All you need to do is add another
                event listener. The events loosely couple all components in your application
                together. </para>
            <para>In some cases, event processing requires new commands to be sent to the
                application. An example of this is when an order is received. This could mean the
                customer's account should be debited with the amount of the purchase, and shipping
                must be told to prepare a shipment of the purchased goods. In many applications,
                logic will become more complicated than this: what if the customer didn't pay in
                time? Will you send the shipment right away, or await payment first? The saga is the
                CQRS concept responsible for managing these complex business transactions. </para>
            <para>The building blocks related to event handling and dispatching are explained in
                    <xref linkend="event-processing"/>. Sagas are thoroughly explained in <xref
                    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" linkend="sagas"/>.</para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Querying for data</title>
            <para>The thin data layer in between the user interface and the data sources provides a
                clearly defined interface to the actual query implementation used. This data layer
                typically returns read-only DTO objects containing query results. The contents of
                these DTO's are typically driven by the needs of the User Interface. In most cases,
                they map directly to a specific view in the UI (also referred to as table-per-view). </para>
            <para>Axon does not provide any building blocks for this part of the application. The
                main reason is that this is very straightforward and doesn't differ from the layered
                architecture.</para>
        </simplesect>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Axon Module Structure</title>
        <para>Axon Framework consists of a number of modules that target specific problem areas of
            CQRS. Depending on the exact needs of your project, you will need to include one or more
            of these modules.</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Main modules</title>
            <para>Axon's main modules are the modules that have been thorouhgly tested and are
                robust enough to use in demanding production environments. The maven groupId of all
                these modules is <code>org.axonframework</code>.</para>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Axon Core</title>
                <para>The Core module contains, as the name suggests, the Core components of Axon.
                    If you use a single-node setup, this module is likely to provide all the
                    components you need. All other Axon modules depend on this module, so it must
                    always be available on the classpath.</para>
            </simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Axon Test</title>
                <para>The Test modules contains test fixtures that you can use to test Axon based
                    components, such as your Command Handlers, Aggregates and Sagas. You typically
                    do not need this module at runtime and will only need to be added to the
                    classpath during tests.</para>
            </simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Axon Distributed CommandBus</title>
                <para>The Distributed CommandBus modules contains a CommandBus implementation that
                    can be used to distribute commands over multiple nodes. It comes with a
                    JGroupsConnector that is used to connect DistributedCommandBus implementation on
                    these nodes.</para>
            </simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Axon Disruptor CommandBus</title>
                <para>The SimpleCommandBus implementation provides pretty good performance, but the
                    Disruptor CommandBus module allows you to squeeze more juice out of the same
                    CPU. It provides an implementation that uses the Disruptor (a lightweight
                    high-performance computing framework) to speed up processing.</para>
            </simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Axon AMQP</title>
                <para>The AMQP module provides components that allow you to build up an EventBus
                    using an AMQP-based message broker as distribution mechanism. This allows for
                    guaranteed-delivery, even when the Event Handler node is temporarily
                    unavailable.</para>
            </simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Axon Integration</title>
                <para>The Integration module allows Axon components to be connected to Spring
                    Integration channels. It provides an implementation for the EventBus that uses
                    Spring Integration channels to distribute events as well as a connector to
                    connect another EventBus to a Spring Integration channel.</para>
            </simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Axon Mongo</title>
                <para>MongoDB is a document based NoSQL database. The Mongo module provides an
                    EventStore implementation that stores event streams in a MongoDB
                    database.</para>
            </simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Axon Monitoring JMX</title>
                <para>Several AxonFramework components provide monitoring information. This module
                    publishes that information over JMX. There is no configuration involved. If this
                    module is on the classpath, statistics and monitoring informatin is
                    automatically published over JMX.</para>
            </simplesect>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Incubator modules</title>
            <para>Incubator modules have not undergone the same amount of testing as the main
                modules, are not as well documented, and may therefore not be suitable for demanding
                production environments. They are typically work-in-progress and may have some
                "rough edges". Use these modules at your own peril.</para>
            <para>The maven groupId for incubator modules is
                    <code>org.axonframework.incubator</code>.</para>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Axon Cassandra</title>
                <para>This module aims to provide an implementation of the EventStore that uses
                    Cassandra as backing storage.</para>
            </simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Axon Google App Engine</title>
                <para>The Google App Engine modules provides building blocks that use specific API's
                    provided by GAE, such as an Event Store that uses the DatastoreService and a
                    special XStream based serializer that works around some of the limitations of
                    the GAE platform.</para>
            </simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Axon Redis</title>
                <para>Redis is a key-value based NoSQL store with very high performance
                    characteristics. This module aims to provide an implementation of the EventStore
                    that uses Redis as backing storage.</para>
            </simplesect>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Working with Axon API's</title>
        <annotation>
            <para>CQRS is an architectural pattern, making it impossible to provide a single
                solution that fits all projects. Axon Framework does not try to provide that one
                sulution, obviously. Instead, Axon provides implementations that follow best
                practices and the means to tweak each of those implementations to your specific
                requirements.</para>
            <para>Almost all infrastructure building blocks will provide hook points (such as
                Interceptors, Resolvers, etc.) that allow you to add application-specific behavior
                to those building blocks. In many cases, Axon will provide implementations for those
                hook points that fit most use cases. If required, you can simply implement your
                own.</para>
            <para>Non-infrastructural objects, such as Messages, are generally immutable. This
                ensures that these objects are safe to use in a multi-threaded environment, without
                side-effects.</para>
        </annotation>
        <para>To ensure maximum customizability, all Axon components are defined using interfaces.
            Abstract and concrete implementations are provided to help you on your way, but will
            nowhere be required by the framework. It is always possible to build a completely custom
            implementation of any building block using that interface.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
            <title>Spring Support</title>
            <para>Axon Framework provides extensive support for Spring, but does not require you to
                use Spring in order to use Axon. All components can be configured programmatically
                and do not require Spring on the classpath. However, if you do use Spring, much of
                the configuration is made easier with the use of Spring's namespace support.
                Building blocks, such as the Command Bus, Event Bus and Saga Managers can be
                configured using a single XML element in your Spring Application Context.</para>
            <para>Check out the documentation of each building block for more information on how to
            configure it using Spring.</para>
        </sect1>
</chapter>
