<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ Copyright (c) 2010-2012. Axon Framework
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="sagas">
    <title>Managing complex business transactions</title>
    <para>Not every command is able to completely execute in a single ACID transaction. A very
        common example that pops up quite often as an argument for transactions is the money
        transfer. It is often believed that an atomic and consistent transaction is absolutely
        required to transfer money from one account to another. Well, it's not. On the contrary, it
        is quite impossible to do. What if money is transferred from an account on Bank A, to
        another account on Bank B? Does Bank A acquire a lock in Bank B's database? If the transfer
        is in progress, is it strange that Bank A has deducted the amount, but Bank B hasn't
        deposited it yet? Not really, it's "underway". On the other hand, if something goes wrong
        while depositing the money on Bank B's account, Bank A's customer would want his money back.
        So we do expect some form of consistency, ultimately.</para>
    <para>While ACID transactions are not necessary or even impossible in some cases, some form of
        transaction management is still required. Typically, these transactions are referred to as
        BASE transactions: <emphasis role="bold">B</emphasis>asic <emphasis role="bold"
        >A</emphasis>vailability, <emphasis role="bold">S</emphasis>oft state, <emphasis role="bold"
            >E</emphasis>ventual consistency. Contrary to ACID, BASE transactions cannot be easily
        rolled back. To roll back, compensating actions need to be taken to revert anything that has
        occurred as part of the transaction. In the money transfer example, a failure at Bank B to
        deposit the money, will refund the money in Bank A.</para>
    <para>In CQRS, Sagas are responsible for managing these BASE transactions. They respond on
        Events produced by Commands and may produce new commands, invoke external applications, etc.
        In the context of Domain Driven Design, it is not uncommon for Sagas to be used as
        coordination mechanism between several bounded contexts.</para>
    <sect1>
        <title xml:id="saga">Saga</title>
        <para>A Saga is a special type of Event Listener: one that manages a business transaction.
            Some transactions could be running for days or even weeks, while others are completed
            within a few milliseconds. In Axon, each instance of a Saga is responsible for managing
            a single business transaction. That means a Saga maintains state necessary to manage
            that transaction, continuing it or taking compensating actions to roll back any actions
            already taken. Typically, and contrary to regular Event Listeners, a Saga has a starting
            point and an end, both triggered by Events. While the starting point of a Saga is
            usually very clear, while there could be many ways for a Saga to end.</para>
        <para>In Axon, all Sagas must implement the <code>Saga</code> interface. As with Aggregates,
            there is a Saga implementation that allows you to annotate event handling methods: the
                <code>AbstractAnnotatedSaga</code>.</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Life Cycle</title>
            <para>As a single Saga instance is responsible for managing a single transaction. That
                means you need to be able to indicate the start and end of a Saga's Life
                Cycle.</para>
            <para>The <code>AbstractAnnotatedSaga</code> allows you to annotate Event Handlers with
                an annotation (<code>@SagaEventHandler</code>). If a specific Event signifies the
                start of a transaction, add another annotation to that same method:
                    <code>@StartSaga</code>. This annotation will create a new saga and invoke its
                event handler method when a matching Event is published.</para>
            <para>By default, a new Saga is only started if no suitable existing Saga (of the same
                type) can be found. You can also force the creation of a new Saga instance by
                setting the <code>forceNew</code> property on the <code>@StartSaga</code> annotation
                to <code>true</code>.</para>
            <para>Ending a Saga can be done in two ways. If a certain Event always indicates the end
                of a Saga's life cycle, annotate that Event's handler on the Saga with
                    <code>@EndSaga</code>. The Saga's Life Cycle will be ended after the invocation
                of the handler. Alternatively, you can call <code>end()</code> from inside the Saga
                to end the life cycle. This allows you to conditionally end the Saga.</para>
            <note>
                <para>If you don't use annotation support, you need to properly configure your Saga
                    Manager (see <xref linkend="saga-manager"/> below). To end a Saga's life cycle,
                    make sure the <code>isActive()</code> method of the Saga returns
                        <code>false</code>.</para>
            </note>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Event Handling</title>
            <para>Event Handling in a Saga is quite comparable to that of a regular Event Listener.
                The same rules for method and parameter resolution are valid here. There is one
                major difference, though. While there is a single instance of an Event Listener that
                deals will all incoming events, multiple instances of a Saga may exist, each
                interested in different Events. For example, a Saga that manages a transaction
                around an Order with Id "1" will not be interested in Events regarding Order "2",
                and vice versa.</para>
            <simplesect><title>Using association values</title>
            <para>Instead of publishing all Events to all Saga instances (which would be a complete
                waste of resources), Axon will only publish Events containing properties that the
                Saga has been associated with. This is done using <code>AssociationValue</code>s. An
                    <code>AssociationValue</code> consists of a key and a value. The key represents
                the type of identifier used, for example "orderId" or "order". The value represents
                the corresponding value, "1" or "2" in the previous example.</para>
            <para>The <code>@SagaEventHandler</code> annotation has two attributes, of which
                    <code>associationProperty</code> is the most important one. This is the name of
                the property on the incoming Event that should be used to find associated Sagas. The
                key of the association value is the name of the property. The value is the value
                returned by property's getter method.</para>
            <para>For example, consider an incoming Event with a method "<code>String
                        getOderId()</code>", which returns "123". If a method accepting this Event
                    is annotated with <code>@SagaEventHandler(associationProperty="orderId")</code>,
                    this Event is routed to all Sagas that have been associated with an
                        <code>AssociationValue</code> with key "orderId" and value "123". This may
                    either be exactly one, more than one, or even none at all.</para>
                <para>Sometimes, the name of the property you want to association is not the name of
                    the association you want to use. For example, you have a Saga that matches Sell
                    orders against Buy orders, you could have a Transaction object that contains the
                    "buyOrderId" and a "sellOrderId". If you want the saga to associate that value
                    as "orderId", you can define a different keyName in the
                        <code>@SagaEventHandler</code> annotation. It would then become
                        <code>@SagaEventHandler(associationProperty="sellOrderId",
                        keyName="orderId")</code></para></simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Associating Sagas with Domain Concepts</title>
                <para>When a Saga manages a transaction around one or more domain concepts, such as
                    Order, Shipment, Invoice, etc, that Saga needs to be associated with instances
                    of those concepts. An association requires two parameters: the key, which
                    identifies the type of association (Order, Shipment, etc) and a value, which
                    represents the identifier of that concept.</para>
                <para>Associating a Saga with a concept is done in several ways. First of all, when
                    a Saga is newly created when invoking a <code>@StartSaga</code> annotated Event
                    Handler, it is automatically associated with the property identified in the
                        <code>@SagaEventHandler</code> method. Any other association can be created
                    using the <code>associateWith(String key, String/Number value)</code> method.
                    Use the <code>removeAssociationWith(String key, String/Number value)</code>
                    method to remove a specific association.</para>
                <para>Imagine a Saga that has been created for a transaction around an Order. The
                    Saga is automatically associated with the Order, as the method is annotated with
                        <code>@StartSaga</code>. The Saga is responsible for creating an Invoice for
                    that Order, and tell Shipping to create a Shipment for it. Once both the
                    Shipment have arrived and the Invoice has been paid, the transaction is
                    completed and the Saga is closed.</para>
                <para>Here is the code for such a Saga: <programlistingco>
                        <areaspec>
                            <area xml:id="client-generated-id-co" coords="10 41"/>
                            <area xml:id="associate-co" coords="13 78"/>
                            <area xml:id="end1-co" coords="25 20"/>
                            <area xml:id="end2-co" coords="33 20"/>
                        </areaspec>
                        <programlisting language="java">public class OrderManagementSaga extends AbstractAnnotatedSaga {

    private boolean paid = false;
    private boolean delivered = false;
    private transient CommandGateway commandGateway;

    @StartSaga
    @SagaEventHandler(associationProperty = "orderId")
    public void handle(OrderCreatedEvent event) {
        // client generated identifiers
        ShippingId shipmentId = createShipmentId();
        InvoiceId invoiceId = createInvoiceId();
        // associate the Saga with these values, before sending the commands
        associateWith("shipmentId", shipmentId);
        associateWith("invoiceId", invoiceId);
        // send the commands
        commandGateway.send(new PrepareShippingCommand(...));
        commandGateway.send(new CreateInvoiceCommand(...));
    }

    @SagaEventHandler(associationProperty = "shipmentId")
    public void handle(ShippingArrivedEvent event) {
        delivered = true;
        if (paid) {
            end();
        }
    }

    @SagaEventHandler(associationProperty = "invoiceId")
    public void handle(InvoicePaidEvent event) {
        paid = true;
        if (delivered) {
            end();
        }
    }

    // ...

}</programlisting>
                        <calloutlist>
                            <callout arearefs="client-generated-id-co">
                                <para>By allowing clients to generate an identifier, a Saga can be
                                    easily associated with a concept, without the need to a
                                    request-response type command.</para>
                            </callout>
                            <callout arearefs="associate-co">
                                <para>We associate the event with these concepts before publishing
                                    the command. This way, we are guaranteed to also catch events
                                    generated as part of this command.</para>
                            </callout>
                            <callout arearefs="end1-co end2-co">
                                <para>This will end this saga once the invoice is paid and the
                                    shipment has arrived. </para>
                            </callout>
                        </calloutlist>
                    </programlistingco></para>
                <para>Of course, this Saga implementation is far from complete. What should happen
                    if the invoice is not paid in time. What if the shipment cannot be delivered?
                    The Saga should be able to cope with those scenarios as well. </para>
            </simplesect>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Keeping track of Deadlines</title>
            <para>It is easy to make a Saga take action when something happens. After all, there is
                an Event to notify the Saga. But what if you want your Saga to do something when
                <emphasis>nothing</emphasis> happens? That's what deadlines are used for. In 
                invoices, that's typically several weeks, while the confirmation of a
                credit card payment should occur within a few seconds.</para>
            <para>In Axon, you can use an <code>EventScheduler</code> to schedule an Event for
                publication. In the example of an Invoice, you'd expect that invoice to be paid
                within 30 days. A Saga would, after sending the <code>CreateInvoiceCommand</code>,
                schedule an <code>InvoicePaymentDeadlineExpiredEvent</code> to be published in 30
                days. The EventScheduler returns a <code>ScheduleToken</code> after scheduling an
                Event. This token can be used to cancel the schedule, for example when a payment of
                an Invoice has been received.</para>
            <para>Axon provides two EventScheduler implementations: a pure Java one and one using
                Quartz 2 as a backing scheduling mechanism.</para>
            <simplesect>
                <title><code>SimpleEventScheduler</code></title>
                <para>This pure-Java implementation of the <code>EventScheduler</code> uses a
                        <code>ScheduledExecutorService</code> to schedule Event publication.
                    Although the timing of this scheduler is very reliable, it is a pure in-memory
                    implementation. Once the JVM is shut down, all schedules are lost. This makes
                    this implementation unsuitable for long-term schedules.</para>
                <para>The <code>SimpleEventScheduler</code> needs to be configured with an
                        <code>EventBus</code> and a <code>SchedulingExecutorService</code> (see the
                    static methods on the <code>java.util.concurrent.Executors</code> class for
                    helper methods).</para>
            </simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title><code>QuartzEventScheduler</code></title>
                <para>The <code>QuartzEventScheduler</code> is a more reliable and enterprise-worthy
                    implementation. Using Quartz as underlying scheduling mechanism, it provides
                    more powerful features, such as persistence, clustering and misfire management.
                    This means Event publication is guaranteed. It might be a little late, but it
                    will be published.</para>
                <para>It needs to be configured with a Quartz <code>Scheduler</code> and an
                        <code>EventBus</code>. Optionally, you may set the name of the group that
                    Quartz jobs are scheduled in, which defaults to "AxonFramework-Events".</para>
            </simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Scheduled Events and Transactions</title>
                <para>One or more components will be listening for scheduled Events. These
                    components might rely on a Transaction being bound to the Thread that invokes
                    them. Scheduled Events are published by Threads managed by the
                        <code>EventScheduler</code>. To manage transactions on these threads, you
                    can configure a <code>TransactionManager</code> or
                        a<code>UnitOfWorkFactory</code> that creates Transaction Bound Unit of
                    Work.</para>
                <note>
                    <para>Spring users can use the <code>QuartzEventSchedulerFactoryBean</code> or
                            <code>SimpleEventSchedulerFactoryBean</code> for easier configuration.
                        It allows you to set the PlatformTransactionManager directly.</para>
                </note>
            </simplesect>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Injecting Resources</title>
            <para>Sagas generally do more than just maintaining state based on Events. They interact
                with external components. To do so, they need access to the Resources necessary to
                address to components. Usually, these resources aren't really part of the Saga's
                state and shouldn't be persisted as such. But once a Saga is reconstructed, these
                resources must be injected before an Event is routed to that instance.</para>
            <para>For that purpose, there is the <code>ResourceInjector</code>. It is used by the
                    <code>SagaRepository</code> (for existing Saga instances) and the
                    <code>SagaFactory</code> (for newly created instances) to inject resources into
                a Saga. Axon provides a <code>SpringResourceInjector</code>, which injects annotated
                fields and methods with Resources from the Application Context, and a
                    <code>SimpleResourceInjector</code>, which detects setters and injects resources
                which have been registered with it.</para>
            <tip>
                <title>Mark fields holding injected resources <code>transient</code></title>
                <para>Since resources should not be persisted with the Saga, make sure to add the
                        <code>transient</code> keyword to those fields. This will prevent the
                    serialization mechanism to attempt to write the contents of these fields to the
                    repository. The repository will automatically re-inject the required resources
                    after a Saga has been deserialized.</para>
            </tip>
            <simplesect>
                <title>SimpleResourceInjector</title>
                <para>The <code>SimpleResourceInjector</code> uses, as the name suggests, a simple
                    mechanism to detect required resources. It scans the methods of a Saga to find
                    one that starts with "set" and contains a single parameter, of a type that
                    matches with of its known resources.</para>
                <para>The <code>SimpleResourceInjector</code> is initialized with a collection of
                    objects that a Saga may depend on. If a Saga has a setter method (name starts
                    with "set" and has a single parameter) in which a resource can be passed, it
                    will invoke that method.</para>
            </simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title>SpringResourceInjector</title>
                <para>The <code>SpringResourceInjector</code> uses Spring's dependency injection
                    mechanism to inject resources into an aggregate. This means you can use setter
                    injection or direct field injection if you require. The method or field to be
                    injected needs to be annotated in order for Spring to recognize it as a
                    dependency, for example with <code>@Autowired</code>.</para>
                <para>Note that when you use the Axon namespace in Spring to create a Saga
                    Repository or Saga Manager, the <code>SpringResourceInjector</code> is
                    configured by default. For more information about wiring Sagas with Spring, see
                        <xref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" linkend="spring-sagas"
                    />.</para>
            </simplesect>
            
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Saga Infrastructure</title>
        <para>Events need to be redirected to the appropriate Saga instances. To do so, some
            infrastructure classes are required. The most important components are the
                <code>SagaManager</code> and the <code>SagaRepository</code>.</para>
        <sect2 xml:id="saga-manager">
            <title>Saga Manager</title>
            <para>The <code>SagaManager</code> is responsible for redirecting Events to the
                appropriate Saga instances and managing their life cycle. There are two
                    <code>SagaManager</code> implementations in Axon Framework: the
                    <code>AnnotatedSagaManager</code>, which provides the annotation support and the
                    <code>SimpleSagaManager</code>, which is less powerful, but doesn't force you
                into using annotations.</para>
            <para>Sagas operate in a highly concurrent environment. Multiple Events may reach a Saga
                at (nearly) the same time. This means that Sagas need to be thread safe. By default,
                Axon's <code>SagaManager</code> implementations will synchronize access to a Saga
                instance. This means that only one thread can access a Saga at a time, and all
                changes by one thread are guaranteed to be visible to any successive threads (a.k.a
                happens-before order in the Java Memory Model). Optionally, you may switch this
                locking off, if you are sure that your Saga is completely thread safe on its own.
                Just <code>setSynchronizeSagaAccess(false)</code>. When disabling synchronization,
                do take note of the fact that this will allow a Saga to be invoked while it is in
                the process of being stored by a repository. The result may be that a Saga is stored
                in an inconsistent state first, and overwritten by it's actual state later.</para>
            <simplesect>
                <title>SimpleSagaManager</title>
                <para>This is by far the least powerful of the two implementations, but it doesn't
                    require the use of annotations. The <code>SimpleSagaManager</code> needs to be
                    configured with a number of resources. Its constructor requires the type of Saga
                    it manages, the <code>SagaRepository</code>, an
                        <code>AssociationValueResolver</code>, a <code>SagaFactory</code> and the
                        <code>EventBus</code>. The <code>AssociationValueResolver</code> is a
                    component that returns a <code>Set</code> of <code>AssociationValue</code> for a
                    given Event.</para>
                <para>Then, you should also configure the types of Events the SagaManager should
                    create new instances for. This is done through the
                        <code>setEventsToAlwaysCreateNewSagasFor</code> and
                        <code>setEventsToOptionallyCreateNewSagasFor</code> methods. They both
                    accept a List of Event classes.</para>
            </simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title>AnnotatedSagaManager</title>
                <para>This SagaManager implementation uses annotations on the Sagas themselves to
                    manage the routing and life cycle of that Saga. As a result, this manager allows
                    all information about the life cycle of a Saga to be available inside the Saga
                    class itself. It can also manage any number of saga types. That means only a
                    single AnnotatedSagaManager is required, even if you have multiple types of
                    Saga.</para>
                <para>The <code>AnnotatedSagaManager</code> is constructed using a SagaRepository, a
                    SagaFactory (optional) and a vararg array of Saga classes. If no
                        <code>SagaFactory</code> is provided, a <code>GenericSagaFactory</code> is
                    used. It assumes that all Saga classes have a public no-arg constructor.</para>
                <para>If you use Spring, you can use the <code>axon</code> namespace to configure an
                    AnnotatedSagaManager. The supported Saga types are provided as a comma separated
                    list. This will also automatically configure a SpringResourceInjector, which
                    injects any annotated fields with resources from the Spring Application
                    Context.</para>
                <programlisting language="xml">&lt;axon:saga-manager id="sagaManager" saga-factory="optionalSagaFactory"
                   saga-repository="sagaRepository" event-bus="eventBus">
    &lt;axon:types>
        fully.qualified.ClassName,
        another.fq.ClassName
    &lt;/axon:types>
&lt;/axon:saga-manager></programlisting>
            </simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Asynchronous Event Handling for Sagas</title>
                <para>As with Event Listeners, it is also possible to asynchronously handle events
                    for sagas. To handle events asynchronously, the SagaManager needs to be
                    configured with an <code>Executor</code> implementation. The
                        <code>Executor</code> supplies the threads needed to process the events
                    asynchronously. Often, you'll want to use a thread pool. You may, if you want,
                    share this thread pool with other asynchronous activities.</para>
                <para>When an executor is provided, the SagaManager will automatically use it to
                    find associated Saga instances and dispatch the events each of these instances.
                    The SagaManager will guarantee that for each Saga instance, all events are
                    processed in the order they arrive. For optimization purposes, this guarantee
                    does not count in between Sagas.</para>
                <para>Because Transactions are often Thread bound, you may need to configure a
                    Transaction Manager with the SagaManager. This transaction manager is invoked
                    before and after each invocation to the Saga Repository and before and after
                    each batch of Events has been processed by the Saga itself.</para>
                <para>In a Spring application context, a Saga Manager can be marked as asynchronous
                    by adding the <code>executor</code> and optionally the
                        <code>transaction-manager</code> attributes to the <code>saga-manager</code>
                    element, as shown below. The <code>processor-count</code> attribute defines the
                    number of threads that should process the
                    sagas.<programlisting language="xml">&lt;axon:saga-manager id="sagaManager" saga-factory="optionalSagaFactory"
                   saga-repository="sagaRepository" event-bus="eventBus">
    &lt;axon:async processor-count="10" executor="myThreadPool" transaction-manager="txManager"/>
    &lt;axon:types>
        fully.qualified.ClassName,
        another.fq.ClassName
    &lt;/axon:types>
&lt;/axon:saga-manager></programlisting>The
                    transaction-manager should point to a <code>PlatformTransactionManager</code>,
                    Spring's interface for transaction managers. Generally you can use the same
                    transaction manager as the other components in your application (e.g.
                        <code>JpaTransactionManager</code>).</para>
                <note>
                    <title>Exceptions while processing Events</title>
                    <para>Since the processing is asynchronous, Exceptions cannot be propagated to
                        the components publishing the Event. Exceptions raised by Sagas while
                        handling an Event are logged and discarded. When an exception occurs while
                        persisting Saga state, the SagaManager will retry persisting the Saga at a
                        later stage. If there are incoming Events, they are processed using the
                        in-memory representation, re-attemtping the persistence later on.</para>
                    <para>When shutting down the application, the SagaManager will do a final
                        attempt to persist the Sagas to their repository, and give up if it does not
                        succeed, allowing the application to finish the shutdown process.</para>
                </note>
            </simplesect>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Saga Repository</title>
            <para>The <code>SagaRepository</code> is responsible for storing and retrieving Sagas,
                for use by the <code>SagaManager</code>. It is capable of retrieving specific Saga
                instances by their identifier as well as by their Association Values.</para>
            <para>There are some special requirements, however. Since concurrency in Sagas is a very
                delicate procedure, the repository must ensure that for each conceptual Saga
                instance (with equal identifier) only a single instance exists in the JVM.</para>
            <para>Axon provides three <code>SagaRepository</code> implementations: the
                    <code>InMemorySagaRepository</code>, the <code>JpaSagaRepository</code> and the
                    <code>MongoSagaRepository</code>.</para>
            <simplesect>
                <title><code>InMemorySagaRepository</code></title>
                <para>As the name suggests, this repository keeps a collection of Sagas in memory.
                    This is the simplest repository to configure and the fastest to use. However, it
                    doesn't provide any persistence. If the JVM is shut down, any stored Saga is
                    lost. This implementation is particularly suitable for testing and some very
                    specialized use cases.</para>
            </simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title><code>JpaSagaRepository</code></title>
                <para>The <code>JpaSagaRepository</code> uses JPA to store the state and Association
                    Values of Sagas. Saga's do no need any JPA annotations; Axon will serialize the
                    sagas using a <code>Serializer</code> (similar to Event serialization, you can
                    use either a <code>JavaSerializer</code> or an
                    <code>XStreamSerializer</code>).</para>
                <para>The JpaSagaRepository is configured with a JPA <code>EntityManager</code>, a
                        <code>ResourceInjector</code> and a <code>Serializer</code>. Optionally, you
                    can choose whether to explicitly flush the <code>EntityManager</code>after each
                    operation. This will ensure that data is sent to the database, even before a
                    transaction is committed. the default is to use explicit flushes.</para>
            </simplesect>
            <simplesect>
                <title><code>MongoSagaRepository</code></title>
                <para>Similar to the <code>JpaSagaRepository</code>, the
                        <code>MongoSagaRepository</code> stores the Saga instances and their
                    associations in a database. The <code>MongoSagaRepository</code> stores sagas in
                    a single Collection in a MongoDB database. Per Saga instance, a single document
                    is created.</para>
                <para>The MongoSagaRepository also ensures that at any time, only a single Saga
                    instance exists for any unique Saga in a single JVM. This ensures that no state
                    changes are lost due to concurrency issues.</para>
            </simplesect>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Caching</title>
            <para>If a database backed Saga Repository is used, saving and loading Saga instances
                may be a relatively expensive operation. Especially in situations where the same
                Saga instance is invoked multiple times within a short timespan, a cache can be
                beneficial to the application's performance.</para>
            <para>Axon provides the <code>CachingSagaRepository</code> implementation. It is a Saga
                Repository that wraps another repository, which does the actual storage. When
                loading Sagas or Association Values, the <code>CachingSagaRepository</code> will
                first consult its caches, before delegating to the wrapped repository. When storing
                information, all call are always delegated, to ensure that the backing storage
                always has a consistent view on the Saga's state.</para>
            <para>To configure caching, simply wrap any Saga repository in a
                    <code>CachingSagaRepository</code>. The constructor of the CachingSagaRepository
                takes three parameters: the repository to wrap and the caches to use for the
                Association Values and Saga instances, respectively. The latter two arguments may
                refer to the same cache, or to different ones. This depends on the eviction
                requirements of your specific application.</para>
            <simplesect>
                <title>Spring namespace support</title>
                <para>Spring users can use the <code>&lt;axon:cache-config></code> element to add
                    caching behavior to a <code>&lt;axon:jpa-saga-repository></code> element. It is
                    configured with two cache references (which may refer to the same cache): one
                    which stores the cached Saga instances, and one that stores the
                    associations.<programlisting>&lt;axon:jpa-saga-repository id="cachingSagaRepository">
    &lt;axon:cache-config saga-cache="sagaCacheRef" associations-cache="associationCacheRef"/>
&lt;/axon:jpa-saga-repository></programlisting></para>
            </simplesect>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
